Finding Aid for Ann Arbor (Mich.) records, 1830-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor (Mich.) records
1830-2002
Ann Arbor (Mich.)
85479; Cc/2; CC oversize
The records of the city of Ann Arbor, Michigan include council proceedings (1834-1919); assessment rolls (1830, 1839, and 1958-1959); scrapbooks relating to city government (1904-1951); and records and photographs detailing the city’s waste management and recycling program beginning in the 1980s. Miscellaneous materials include plats of the wards, 1912; election returns, 1847-1852; records of the former city of East Ann Arbor and the Village of Ann Arbor (Lower Town); and minutes of the Ann Arbor Park Commission (1905-1956). Also of interest are files concerning the Ann Arbor Railroad and the city’s street railway and interurban system.
13 linear feet in 14 boxes
37 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The council minutes and scrapbooks were received from various offices within the city government (donor no. 2054 ) in multiple accessions. The provenance of the other materials is unclear.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Records maintained by the city government of Ann Arbor, Michigan.
The records of the city of Ann Arbor, Michigan include council proceedings (1834-1919); assessment rolls (1830, 1839, and 1958-1959); scrapbooks relating to city government (1904-1951); and records and photographs detailing the city’s waste management and recycling program beginning in the 1980s. Miscellaneous materials include plats of the wards, 1912; election returns, 1847-1852; records of the former city of East Ann Arbor and the Village of Ann Arbor (Lower Town); and minutes of the Ann Arbor Park Commission (1905-1956). Also of interest are files concerning the Ann Arbor Railroad and the city’s street railway and interurban system.
The series in this record group include: Election returns; Bonds; Assessment Rolls; Miscellaneous; City of East Ann Arbor; Council proceedings; Scrapbooks; Ann Arbor Park Commission; Village of Ann Arbor (Lower Town); Photographs; Recycling and Environmental Issues; and Other City Records.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Charter Commission (Ann Arbor, Mich.: 1920); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Ann Arbor Railroad Company.; Ann Arbor Street Railway Company.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Recycling (Waste, etc.)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Refuse and refuse disposal--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Street-railroads--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; East Ann Arbor (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Lower Town (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Park Commission.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Business districts--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; City and town halls--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; City Hall (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Election Returns
  - 1847-1852, 6 folders (Box 1)
- Bonds
  - Public Official Bonds
    - 1877 (Box 1)
    - 1905-1909 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1952, 14 folders (Box 1)
    - 1955-1969, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bank Bonds
    - 1898-1914, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1916-1935, 7 folders (Box 1)
- Assessment Rolls
  - 1830 (Box 1)
  - 1839 (Box 1)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 26)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 27)
    Continued
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 28)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 29)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 30)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 31)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 32)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 33)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 34)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 35)
  - 1958, 1 volumes (Volume 36)
  - (incomplete), 1959; 1 volumes (Volume 37)
- Miscellaneous
  - Proceedings of meeting to consider proposed art museum, 1913 (Box 1)
  - List of names of original settlers (Box 1)
  - Plats of the seven wards, 1912; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning the street railway and interurbans, 1889-1913; 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning the Ann Arbor Railroad, 1902-1914; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Claims and Petitions, 1889-1929; 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Ordinances, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Permits for Removing Buildings, 1928-1956; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning the vote on the purchase of the Ann Arbor Water Company, 1913 (Box 2)
  - Petition for charter revision, 1916 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning the charter commission, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Charters and charter amendments, 1923-1956 (Box 2)
  - Land certificate (Folder Cc)
- City of East Ann Arbor
  - Undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1946-1949, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - 1950-1956, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - Board of Appeals Record book, 1949-1955 (Box 3)
- Council proceedings
  (All council proceedings after 1891 were published and a fairly complete set can be found in the printed works collection along with an index to both the manuscript and printed proceedings.)
  - Rough draft of a city council proceedings, 1876 (Box 3)
  - 1834-1845 (also includes accounts, 1857-1861) (Box 3)
  - 1847-1868, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Excerpts from council proceedings regarding the Civil War, 1861-1866 (Box 3)
  - 1868-1891 (Volume 14)
  - 1868-1891 (Volume 15)
  - 1868-1891 (Volume 16)
  - 1868-1891 (Volume 17)
  - 1868-1891 (Volume 18)
  - 1897-1919 (Volume 19)
  - 1897-1919 (Volume 20)
  - 1897-1919 (Volume 21)
  - 1897-1919 (Volume 22)
  - 1897-1919 (Volume 23)
  - 1897-1919 (Volume 24)
  - 1897-1919 (Volume 25)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 1)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 2)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 3)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 4)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 5)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 6)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 7)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 8)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 9)
  - 1904-1951 (Volume 10)
  - (mainly regarding police and fire department personnel and activities), 1981-1989 (Volume 11)
  - 1963, 1965 (Volume 12)
  - (downtown clean-up, beautification, etc.), 1965 (Volume 13)
- Ann Arbor Park Commission
  - Minute books, 1905-1956; 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
- Village of Ann Arbor (Lower Town)
  - Minute book of the president and trustees, 1859-1861; 1 volumes (Box 4)
- Photographs
  - Views of downtown Ann Arbor and of the new city building, circa 1962-1969; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Waste Management and Environmental Issues
  - News clippings, in binders
    - 1978-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 5)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 5)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 5)
    - 1997-2002 (Box 5)
    - 1989-1994, 1 volumes (Box 6)
      (arranged by following topics: Compost, Ecology Center, Materials Recovery Facility, Landfill, Recycle Ann Arbor, Recycling Ordinance)
  - "City of Ann Arbor Landfill Oral History Project"
    - History entitled compiled by Ann Sibole, 2000; 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Interviews, 2000; 6 audiocassettes (Box 6)
      (transcriptions of tapes not included)
    - Working files (Box 6)
      (include some photographs)
  - Dept of Solid Waste documents, 8 microfiche cards
    - Integrated solid waste management strategy for the Ann Arbor area, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Recycle Ann Arbor service contract, effective, July 1990; August 1990 (Box 6)
    - Recycle Ann Arbor: residential recycling collection service agreement (Box 6)
    - Disposing of commercial trash: 1990 survey of commercial establishments, 1990 and Multi-family housing solid waste survey for Ann Arbor, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Workshops: "Waste Reduction Workshops," Washtenaw County School Districts 1995 and "Pollution Prevention in School" 1992, 1 volumes (Box 6)
  - Landfill Reuse Concept Plan Study and related miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Solid waste / recycling advertisements and informational brochures, 1 folders (Box 6)
    (see also oversize box 14)
  - Earth Day
    - Activities and working files, 1999-2005; 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Informational material (Box 6)
    - Earth Day posters (Box 14)
  - Announcement of events and recycling information, 2 folders (Box 14)
    (contents taken from album)
  - Photographic slides relating to the city's recycling / composting program, 4 slide trays (Box 7)
  - Photographic slides relating to the city's recycling / composting program, 1 slide trays; 3 volumes (Box 8)
  - Photographic slides relating to the city's recycling / composting program (Box 9)
    (in small slide cartons; unprocessed)
  - Photograph prints relating to the city's recycling / composting program and to department personnel and activities (Box 10)
  - Photograph prints relating to the city's recycling / composting program and to department personnel and activities (Box 11)
  - Videotapes, VHS
    - Recycling is Easy: Make it Second Nature (Box 11)
    - Recycle Plus: Commercial Recycling in the City of Ann Arbor (Box 11)
    - Recycle Ann Arbor; 25th anniversary program (Box 11)
- Other city records
  - City of Ann Arbor Diversity Project; Policies and procedures review, March 31, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Diversity training handbook and training material, 1 volumes (Box 12)
  - "To be or not to be"; that is the question relating to diversity project, 1 volumes (Box 12)
  - Organizational retreat workbook, 1996; 1 volumes (Box 12)
  - Internal Communications Directory, November 1999 (Box 13)
  - Comprehensive Annual Financial Report (some gaps), 1983-1995; 6 volumes (Box 13)
  - City of Ann Arbor Annual Report Fiscal Year
    - 1981-1982 (Box 13)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 13)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 13)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 13)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 13)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 13)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 13)
  - City of Ann Arbor, Michigan, First city-wide services survey; citizen responses to services, spending, revenue sources, service delivery, and important issues, May 1998 (Box 13)
  - Ann Arbor city employee's newsletters (Box 13)
Related Material
The library has a separate collection of city publications, including newsletters For the People and Waste Watcher. Other related materials include city council proceedings (beginning in 1891) and a collection of miscellaneous city and departmental publications.